<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Twelve generall arguments proving that the ceremonies imposed upon the ministers of the gospell in England, by our prelates, are unlawfull; and therefore that the ministers of the gospell, for the bare and sole omission of them in church service, for conscience sake, are most unjustlie charged of disloyaltie to his Maiestie.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113554</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848787</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13901</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16624)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13901)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 627:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Twelve generall arguments proving that the ceremonies imposed upon the ministers of the gospell in England, by our prelates, are unlawfull; and therefore that the ministers of the gospell, for the bare and sole omission of them in church service, for conscience sake, are most unjustlie charged of disloyaltie to his Maiestie.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Bradshaw.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Arguments proving that the ceremonies imposed upon the, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Appended, with caption title: An addition.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page mutilated, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:1"/>
            <p>Twelve generall Arguments, Proving that the Ceremonies impoſed upon the Miniſters of the Goſpell in <hi>England,</hi> by our Prelates, are unlawfull; And therefore that the Miniſters of the Goſpell, for the bare and ſole omiſſion of them in Church Service, for conſcience ſake, are moſt unjuſtlie charged of diſloyaltie to his <hi>Maiestie.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. 18.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>If I have ſpoken evill, beare witneſſe of the evill:</l>
               <l>But if I have ſpoken well, why ſmiteſt thou mee?</l>
            </q>
            <p>1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, We come not as voluntaries into this field of Contention, but draug'd into it by the very haires of our head: If our cauſe bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighteous and good, Thou wilt eaſily graunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in ſo great Imputations and Extremities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nflicted upon us for the ſame) that we can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe no leſſe, Then give reaſons for our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd it. All the favour I require of thee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, That thou wouldest looke into our cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not by the flaſhing lightninges, that come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of the mouthes of our Adverſaries the Prelates) but by the light of our owne Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb facs="tcp:13901:3"/> by which if thou ſhalt ſee the goodnes of our cauſe, and innocencie of our perſons, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imbrace it with vs. And in pitie pray fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs, (that without ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience) wee may endure patientli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and meekely, what ſo ever God ſhall ſuffer to bee inflicted vpon vs for the ſame; in theſe wicked and licentious times.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:3"/>
            <head>The firſt Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All Wil-worſhip is ſinne.</item>
               <item>To uſe theſe Ceremonies in Church Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in manner and forme preſcribed, is a Wil-worſhip.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> To uſe them is ſinne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition can not be denied, for the Apoſtle Paule plainly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Wil-worſhip.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption may thus be proved:
<list type="syllogism">
                  <item>All partes of Divine Service and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, impoſed only by the wil and pleaſure of Man, upon the Ministers of Divine Service, and that of neceſsitie, to be done, is Will-worſhip.</item>
                  <item>But to uſe theſe Ceremonies in manner and forme preſcribed, is to uſe ſuch Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies as are 1. partes of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Worſhip, <hi>2.</hi> impoſed onely by the pleaſure and will of Men, upon the
<pb facs="tcp:13901:4"/> Ministers of Divine Service, <hi>3.</hi> 9 neceſsitie to bee done therein,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe theſe Ceremonies in manner an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forme preſcribed, is a Wil-worſhip.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſition is as cleare as the Sunne at noone-day.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption hath three parts, 1. That they are parts of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service.</p>
            <p>This is proved evidently by this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument:
<list type="syllogism">
                  <item>All Mysticall and Eccleſiaſticall Rites and formes of Divine Service, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d by Eccleſiasticall authoritie, to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ministeriall actions in the ſolemne Worſhip of God, and performed in that manner, and having that uſe in Divine Service, that if God ſhould but ratifie and confirme the ſame uſe, they ſhould then be parts of his true Worſhip, (I ſay) all ſuch Ceremonies are uſed as partes of Divine Worſhip</item>
                  <item>But theſe Ceremonies in controverſie,
<pb facs="tcp:13901:4"/> are either all, or the greateſt parte of them ſuch.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey are partes of Divine Worſhip and Service.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſition cannot with any modeſt face bee denied; For els how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould a ſole Divine ratification of the preſent uſe of them, make them partes of his true Worſhip? if they were not uſed as partes of his Worſhip before.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is as manifeſt, For if Chriſt ſhould by ſome Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from heaven ſignifie, That it is his will that a Miniſter in Divine Service ſhould weare a white linnen garment, In Baptiſme make the ſigne of a Croſſe, To theſe endes and purpoſes that are expreſſed in the Service booke, then certainly they ſhould be eſſentiall parts of his Divine Worſhip, els the Iewiſh Rites and Ceremonies and our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are no partes thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:5"/>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Aſſumption<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the 1. Syllogiſme.</p>
            <q>That they are impoſed onely upon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſure and will of man.</q>
            <p>This is evident. For thoſe things th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God leaves as indifferent to the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and diſcretion of man to doe or leav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> undone, being impoſed by man upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man, are impoſed onely upon the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and pleaſure of man.</p>
            <p>The 3. part of the Aſſumption is:
<q>That they are of Neceſsitie to be don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Divine Seruice.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which is alſo out of all doubt, For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Miniſter ſtandes bound to doe them upon paine of ſuſpenſion and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: and God muſt haue no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Worſhip in England, except it be adminiſtred in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Upon all this it followes, <hi>That to uſe theſe Ceremonies in manner and forme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, is to uſe ſuch Ceremonies, as are partes of Divine worſhip impoſed onely by the will of Man, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:5"/>
            <head>The 2. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>It is a ſinne against God for him that is by way of Excellencie a ſervaunt of IESVS Christ, (without a preciſe and direct warrant from him) at any time, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Solemne Worſhip of God) to give ſpeciall Honour to Antichrist and his members,</item>
               <item>But to uſe theſe Ceremonies, is in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner aforeſaid, to give ſpeciall Honour to Antichrist and his members,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> It is a ſinne against God to uſe them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is manifeſt &amp; cleare to any that have an eye of Reaſon and any light of Divinitie ſhyning in it. For what is a ſinne if this be not: That a Servaunt of Ieſus Chriſt, even then when hee is in the Service of Chriſte, ſhould performe ſpeciall Honour and Service to Antichriſt, or any of his limmes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:6"/>
            <p>The Aſſumption is prooved (If our adverſaries will graunt it, that the Pope is Antichriſt, and that all the viſible members of his Church, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him their ſupreame head, are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of him) by this reaſon.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>Such a Conformitie to Antichrist and his Members in the Ceremonies of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Forme of Divine worſhip, as is not only beſides the word of God, but in a ſpeciall manner derogatorie to all refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches that have departed from the Synagogue of Rome, is a ſpeciall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to Antichrist and his members.</item>
               <item>But to uſe theſe Ceremonies in Divine Worſhip, is ſuch a Conformitie to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ and his members,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe theſe Ceremonies, in that manner aforeſaid, is to give ſpeciall honor to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist and his members.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb facs="tcp:13901:6"/> For if it ſhould bee a ſpeciall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to the Biſhops of England &amp; their conformed Cleargie: For the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Scotland, voluntarily to leave conformitie to the Churches of the low Countries, France, &amp; Germanie, and to conforme them ſelves in Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and Forme of Divine worſhip to the Prelaticall Cleargie of England: It muſt needes bee a ſpeciall honour to Antichriſt and his members, for anie to doe the like to them.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is thus proved:
<list type="syllogism">
                  <item>For a Minister of Ieſus Christ to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme him ſelf in ſuch peculiar Rites, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and formes of Divine Service to Antichrist and his members, as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reformed Churches have reiected for vaine, fooliſh, and ſuperstitious, is in a ſpeciall manner derogatorie to all other reformed Churches.</item>
                  <item>But to uſe theſe Ceremonies in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, is in that manner to Conforme him ſelfe.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13901:7"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is in a ſpeciall manner derogatorie to all other Reformed Churches.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Both partes of the Syllogiſme are ſuch as may eaſilie bee prooved, if they bee denied.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:7"/>
            <head>The 3. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All worſhip more then Civill, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to any beſides God, is a ſinne.</item>
               <item>To uſe theſe Ceremonies in manner and forme preſcribed, is to performe a more then civill honor (even a Religious) onely to a humane Power and Authoritie,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe theſe Ceremonies, is to ſinne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition needs no proofe, For there is no midle Honor betweene Civill and Divine, and therefore that which is more then Civill, is Divine. Now Divine Honor is to be give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only to God, who will not have his Glorie given unto another.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is thus proved:
<list type="syllogism">
                  <item>If theſe Ceremonies bee Religious Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and all Religious Ceremonies bee
<pb facs="tcp:13901:8"/> a part of Divine worſhip, performed to that authoritie that instituteth &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth them. If alſo the authoritie that instituteth and commandeth them, is but meerely humane, Then the Aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption is true.</item>
                  <item>But the first is true:</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> The latter is true alſo.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſition can not be denied of any reaſonable creature.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption hath three partes:</p>
            <q>I. That theſe Ceremonies are Religious Ceremonies.</q>
            <p>This needes no proofe: For what ſhall we make to be Religious Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, If thoſe Ceremonies be not, That are preſcribed by the Church, to the Church only, tied to Religion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Religious functions, offices, &amp; perſons: To be acted and performed onely in exerciſes of Religion and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, and are myſticall ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes &amp; types of Religious Doctrine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:8"/>
            <q>II. That all Religious Ceremonies are partes of Divine Worſhip.</q>
            <p>This neither ſhould need any proofe, If thoſe that are adverſaries unto us in this cauſe, did not to much preſume of the weaknes of our diſcourſe, and the ſtrength of their owne wit. For there being an externall Divine Worſhipp which properly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſts in the outward Rites and Ceremonies of Religion: What Ceremonies can be called parts thereof, if ſuch Religious Ceremonies as theſe, bee not? For if bowing the knee, &amp;c. in Divine Worſhip (though it be uſed alſo in Civill Worſhip) be a part of Divine Worſhip, much more are thoſe Ceremonies that are peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly appropriated to Divine Service &amp; Worſhip, &amp; wherein part of the forme thereof is made to conſiſt. But it may (for further ſatiſfying of men) be thus proved:
<list type="syllogism">
                  <item>All meere and immediate Actions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are partes of Divine Worſhip.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13901:9"/>
                  <item>All Religious Ceremonies, are meere and immediate Actions of Religion.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> They are partes of Divine Worſhip.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Further, how can a man imagine that a meere Religious and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Act, done by a Servant of God in the ſolemne Service and Worſhip of God, by preciſe Canon of the Church ſhould be no part of Divine Worſhip, Sith all the ſolemne Rites &amp; Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that are uſed in the ſolemne Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of Civil States, (eſpecially ſuch as are done in their preſence) have bene ever reputed partes of Civill Honor &amp; Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie, conſidering that God in his Divine Worſhip, doeth require the whole heart, and all the powers of the Soule during the act of his Worſhip, It were great preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Creature, to preſcribe any Action to man during the ſame Act that is no
<pb facs="tcp:13901:9"/> part thereof: Conſidering that every Action ſo preſcribed muſt of neceſſitie pull a part of the heart from Divine Worſhipp.</p>
            <q>III. That authoritie that instituted them is but merely Humane.</q>
            <p>This is moſt certaine, for if they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtituted by Divine authoritie, They could not bee eſteemed Matters indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent: and ſhould not be in the power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd diſcretion of the Magiſtrate to diſannull them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:10"/>
            <head>The 4. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>If it be lawfull for a Minister of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell without ſinne to uſe theſe Ceremonies in Divine Worſhip: It is lawfull for him upon the ſame occaſion to uſe any Iewiſh, Turkiſh, Paganiſh or Popiſh Ceremonie whatſoeuer.</item>
               <item>But it is not lawfull for the Minister of the Goſpell to uſe in Divine Worſhip, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſame occaſion, any Iewiſh, Popiſh, Paganiſh or Turkiſh Ceremonie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Hee cannot without ſinne uſe theſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Aſſumption cannot for ſhame be denied, We prove the conſequent of the Propoſition.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>If any Iewiſh, Turkiſh, Paganiſh, or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Ceremonies and Rite bee a thing in
<pb facs="tcp:13901:10"/> it owne Nature as indifferent as theſe Ceremonies are and either have, or may haue by ſuch like inſtitution as good uſe, then the conſequent of the Propoſition is true.</item>
               <item>But the first is true.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> The latter is true alſo.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition, as I think, cannot be denied nor the Aſſumption, but by bringing ſom contrarie inſtance in ſom of their Ceremonies: When any ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall be given, this Argument ſhalbee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urther proſecuted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:11"/>
            <head>The 5. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>Everie ſciſmaticall action done by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of the Goſpell is a Sinne.</item>
               <item>To uſe theſe Ceremonies in controverſie are ſciſmaticall actions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe theſe Ceremonies is Sinne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition will bee graunted. I muſt proove the Aſſumption.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All Actions of irregularitie and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formitie to the Catholike church wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in we liue, are ſciſmaticall Actions.</item>
               <item>To uſe theſe Ceremonies in controverſie, are actions of irregularitie, and non con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formitie to the Catholike church wherei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we live.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> The uſe of theſe Ceremonies in contro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſie are ſciſmaticall Actions.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition cannot be denie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for if we be branded with the cole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13901:11"/> ſciſme iuſtly, for denying co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formitie in ſome Ceremonies, but to ſome of our owne particular Churches wherein we live, though we be content, to ioyne with them that uſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: much more ſciſmatiks are they that are not conformable in Rites and Ceremonies to the Catholike Church wherein they live.</p>
            <p>I proove the Aſſumption.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>If all the Protestants, Pastors, Miniſters &amp; Governors living this day in <hi>Europe,</hi> and all the painefull reſident Pastors of our owne countrey (except ſome Nonreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Idoll ſhepheards, ſom that depend upon the prelacie, and ſome other that are forced and conſtreyned to uſe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their will) doe not only refuſe to uſe theſe Ceremonies, but esteeme them vaine, fooliſh and ſuperſtitious: Then the uſe of theſe Ceremonies are actions of irregularitie and non Conformitie to the Catholike Church.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:13901:12"/>
               <item>But the first wilbe prooved true,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> The latter is true alſo.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is evident, by their owne principles: For an irregularitie &amp; non-Conformitie to the Paſtors and Governours of Churches, is an irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie and non-Conformitie to the Churche, for they are reputed the <hi>CHVRCH REPRESENTATIVE:</hi> and if they be to be anathematized, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated that deny The Biſhops and other Miniſters aſſembled in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vocation, to be the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland repreſentative, then ſurely are all the Paſtors of the viſible Churches in Europe, the Catholike Church repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, &amp; thoſe particular Miniſters in this Realme, that ſhall uſe not onely different Ceremonies; but ſuch as they have renounced and forſaken, are ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes and irregular perſons.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is evident in it ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:12"/>
            <head>The 6. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All ſpirituall Communion with thoſe Idolatours amongst whom we live in the mysteries of their Idolatrie and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is ſinne.</item>
               <item>To uſe theſe Ceremonies in Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is a ſpirituall Communion with the Idolatrous Papistes (That doe not onely border round about us, but are tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in infinite numbers to live amongest us) in the mysteries of their Idolat. and Superstition.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe theſe Ceremonies is to ſinne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is his M. own, if Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter B. have made a true report of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference at Hampt. Court, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Ma. confeſſeth, That if wee lived amongſt Idolators, we ought not then to communicate with them in their Rites and Ceremonies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:13"/>
            <p>The Aſſumption is thus prooved.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>If Papistes be Idolators, if we be not onely in league with whole kingdomes of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes bordering upon us and neare unto us, but have many Thouſande profeſſed ones living amongst us: if theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies be ſpeciall myſteries of their Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion if to uſe the ſame Rites that they do in theirs in our ſpirituall and Divine Service, he ſpiritually to communicate with them in the ſame: Then is the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Aſſumption true.</item>
               <item>But wee ſhall be able to prove, as ſone as any ſhall deny, that the first and every parte and parcell thereof is true.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> The later is true alſo.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:13"/>
            <head>The 7. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>To mingle Profane things with Divine, is to ſinne.</item>
               <item>To uſe theſe Ceremonies in Divine Worſhip is to mingle Profane things with Divine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe theſe Ceremonies in Divine Worſhip, is to ſinne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition ſhineth in the eyes of the very Heathen, who have eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it a diſhonor to their Religion &amp; worſhippe, that any profane perſons ſhould be Actors in it, much more that any profane Actions ſhould bee min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with it.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is thus proved.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All peculiar Actions done in Divine Worſhip, that are neither Civill nor holy, are profane.</item>
               <item>Theſe Ceremonies are peculiar actions done
<pb facs="tcp:13901:14"/> in Divine Worſhip, that are neither ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill nor holy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> They are Profane.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition cannot with any ſhew of reaſon be denied, there being no meane betweene theſe in ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as are preſcribed to be done in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service by Canon and Law: For though ſpitting, coughing, hemming, &amp;c. if they be uſed for neceſſitie, bee neither civill, holy, nor profane Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Yet if there ſhould be an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Canon that ſhould require the Miniſter to ſpit at every full period; or the people to hem, and hauke at every tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſition in a Sermon, they muſt needs then be referred to one of theſe three heades, as ſhall eaſily be proved if it be denyed.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is as cleare.</p>
            <p>For firſt his Ma. (with words of great diſgrace and contempt of thoſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:13901:14"/> hold the contrarie): hath lately prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted that they are not urged as holy &amp; Religious matters: And that they are not Civill Actions, hath beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before, for there beeing an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in Reaſon betweene things <hi>Civill &amp; Eccleſiasticall,</hi> though they haue ſome things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to both (as all oppoſites haue) yet it is ridiculous to affirme that thoſe things are Civill, that are meerely Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, and are Actions peculiarly appropriated and tied to Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: For Civill Actions, are performed in Civill affaires, and though there is a common Civilitie alſo to be obſerved even in Divine matters: Yet thoſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions cannot be called Civill, that are uſed onely in Divine Offices and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, no more then thoſe can be called Eccleſiaſticall and Divine that are uſed onely in Civill affaires. For it may be affirmed by as good reaſon, that an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall
<pb facs="tcp:13901:15"/> Officer imployed onely in Eccleſiaſticall matters, is a Civill Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer only. Or a Civill Officer imployed onely in Civill matters is an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Officer only; as that a meere Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall action, done in and by the Church onely, ſhould be a Civill Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:15"/>
            <head>The 8. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>If it be lawfull to uſe theſe Ceremonies in Divine worſhip, it is therefore lawfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are either lawfull in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; or being things in their owne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture indifferent, are made lawfull by the commaundment of the Magistrate to bee uſed in Divine Service.</item>
               <item>But they are neither lawfull in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be uſed, nor therefore lawfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Magistrate commaundes them ſo to be uſed, though they bee Matters in their owne Nature indifferent.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> They are unlawfull to be uſed in Divine Worſhip.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition I think can not be denied, when it is, I hope it may bee prooved.</p>
            <p>The firſt part of the Aſſumption is
<pb facs="tcp:13901:16"/> cleare: For if they were in themſelves lawfull, to be uſed, then might a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel being left to his own diſcretion, by the Magiſtrate, invent, inſtitute, and uſe the like Ceremonies, in the ſame maner without ſinne. For any man left to him ſelfe, may lawfully doe that which of it ſelfe is lawfull and indifferent. But a Miniſter ſhould ſinne againſt God, if hee ſhould of his owne head inſtitute, &amp; uſe the like Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to theſe, though permitted by the Magiſtrate; Except wee ſhould hold, that it is lawfull, for a Miniſter to doe any indifferent thing in Gods Service, for a man may of any indifferent thing, make a Ceremonie like unto one of theſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Aſſumption is thus proved.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>If they bee therefore lawfull, becauſe beeing things in their owne Nature indifferent, the Magistrate commaunds
<pb facs="tcp:13901:16"/> them to be done in Divine Service, Then whatſoever thing (being in it owne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture indifferent) is or ſhalbe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Magistrate is lawfull to bee done in Divine Service.</item>
               <item>But all things that are in them ſelves mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters indifferent, are not lawfull to bee done in Divine Service, though the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhould commaund them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> They are not therefore lawfull to be uſed in Divine ſervice, becauſe the Magiſtrate commandes them, though they be things in their owne nature indifferent.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition cannot be denied, For if ſome things indifferent in their owne Nature being commaunded by the Magiſtrate, are unlawfull: It can be no good Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſay, Theſe things being indifferent are commaunded by the Magiſtrate. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They may lawfully be done. Much-leſſe therefore they ought to be done.
<pb facs="tcp:13901:17"/> Or as the Doctors of <hi>Oxef.</hi> affirme that they binde the conſcience.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is more cleare then the Propoſition. If it be conſidered either what things are indifferent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, or goe under the name and title of indifferent things. Eating &amp; drinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; the avoiding the ſuperfluities of Nature; due benevolence betweene man and wife; ſpinning and carding; killing of Oxen and ſheep, &amp;c. which of themſelves have in them neither vertue nor vice, are therfore indifferent Actions; and yet I thinke none except profeſſed Atheiſtes, but will hold it a foule ſinne to doe ſome of theſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in any Aſſembly, much more in the ſolemne worſhip of God, though the Magiſtrate ſhould commaund the ſame even upon paine of death. But if it be further conſidered, That Carding and Dicing, Maſking and Dauncinge; for Men to put on Woomens apparell,
<pb facs="tcp:13901:17"/> and women mens: Drincking to healthes; Ribald, Stage-playes, &amp;c. are things indifferent to be done even vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lords owne day: May a Miniſter of the Goſpell uppon the Magiſtrates commaundement doe any of theſe in Divine Worſhip. And yet ther is none of theſe, but may have applied unto them by the Witt of Man, a Myſticall and Religious Sence; and then by this Biſh. of Canterburies Rule, They muſt needes be good and lawfull Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: for his principall Argument to proove them lawfull at his laſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of London Miniſters before him, was this.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>They are Ceremonies that teach good Doctrine,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> They are good Ceremonies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Whereas the filthieſt actions and thinges that are may teach good do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The holy Ghoſt reſembleth the
<pb facs="tcp:13901:18"/> ſoule polluted with ſinne, to a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous cloth: A man fallen againe into ſinne, to a Sowe wallowing in the mire: might therfore a filthie ſow and ſuch uncelane clothes be brought into the Church, to be viſible ſhadowes, &amp; repreſentations of ſuch thinges? Nay, what may not by this meanes bee brought into Gods worſhip, &amp; yet by this reaſon be defended to bee a good Ceremonie if the Magiſtrates and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhould decree the ſame? A fooles coate and a beggers, worne in Divine Service, may fitly teach this doctrine <hi>Not many Wiſe, not many Noble:</hi> A Miniſter clothed in ſuch apparel as thoſe that act the Divels part in a playe may teach this, That by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we are lymmes of Sathan and fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands of hell, Men might weare Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens apparell, and Womens Men, The one to teach, That the Church is Chriſtes Wife; The other to teache,
<pb facs="tcp:13901:18"/> That Women in Chriſt are equall to Men. Beare-bayting may teache us, How Chriſt was bayted before the Tribunals of the Phariſies, or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit. But the groſſenes of theſe Aſſertions will appeare in our Speciall Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Ceremonies in particular.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:19"/>
            <head>The 9. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>To Administer unto the Church of God, Sacramentes that are not of Divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, is to ſinne.</item>
               <item>To uſe divers of theſe Ceremonies, viz. The Croſſe in Baptiſme, the Ring in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadge, the Surplice, &amp;c. is to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter unto the Church of God Sacraments that are not of Divine institution:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe theſe Ceremonies, is to ſinne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is graunted of all, both Papiſt and Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is thus prooved.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All mysticall bodily Rites and Signes of ſpirituall grace, administred to the Church of God in his ſolemne ſervice, to confirme grace, and that by him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentes the perſon of Christ, are Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:13901:19"/>
               <item>The greatest part of theſe Ceremonies in controverſie are ſuch, &amp; not of any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Institution.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> To uſe them, is to administer Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes that are not of Divine Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is moſt evident, &amp; can not bee denied of any that beares the face of a Divine.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is as evident, only this one clauſe may bee doubted of: Whether theſe Ceremonies bee admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to confirme Grace, whiche is thus proved.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>Thoſe Ceremonies that are administred to edifie the ſoule and conſciences, are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred to confirme grace.</item>
               <item>Theſe Ceremonies are administred to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie the ſoule and conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> They are administred to confirme Grace.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:20"/>
            <p>The Propoſition can not with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie colour be excepted againſt. For to edifie the ſoule, to confirme grace in the ſoule, and to feede the ſoule, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent.</p>
            <p>The Sacrament of the Supper ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being for this onely cauſe a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe it is a Myſticall Rite, whereby the ſoule ſpiritually feedeth uppon Chriſt. i. is edified in Chriſt: Theſe being Myſtical Rites alſo, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſoule is edified, which it cannot be but alſo by feeding upon Chriſt, It muſt needes follow, That theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are Sacramentes.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is their owne, for when they are urged with this, That all things muſt be done to edification, They hold all with one conſent, That they doe edifie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:20"/>
            <head>The 10. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>It is a Sinne against Christ the ſole Head of the Church, For any one of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, (eſpecially in the Administration of Divine things) either by Worde or Signes, ſolemnely to profeſſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a ſpirituall Homage, to a uſurped ſpirituall authoritie in the Church.</item>
               <item>But to uſe theſe controverted Ceremonies in manner and forme preſcribed, is even in the ſolemne Service of Chriſt, by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Signes, to acknowledge a ſpirituall Homage, to the ſpirituall authoritie of Lord Archbiſhops and Biſhops, which is uſurped.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is a ſinne to uſe theſe Ceremonies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition may not be gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: For all ſpirituall power uſurped over the Churches of God, is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian authoritie, and to profeſſe ſpirituall homage thereunto, is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13901:21"/> ſpirituall homage unto Antichriſt, which muſt needs be a ſinne.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption hath two partes.</p>
            <q>I. That theſe Ceremonies are an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging by ſolemne ſignes, a ſpirituall Homage to the ſpirituall authoritie of Archbiſhops and Biſhops.</q>
            <p>Which is moſt evident; for it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bene proved before, that they are meere Eccleſiaſticall, Religious &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Actions, injoyned by an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and ſpirituall authoritie, They muſt needes be Signes of ſpirituall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the ſame authoritie. For either the doing of a Religious and ſpirituall Action, in obedience to a ſpirituall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, is a Signe of ſpirituall homage, or no Actions can bee a Signe thereof. As therefore a ſerving man being a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill perſon, upon the Biſhops pleaſure, wearing a Tawnie Cote, and a Chaine of Golde, holding vp his Trayne, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bare-headed before him; holding a
<pb facs="tcp:13901:21"/> Trencher at his Table: lighting him to the houſe of office: dreſſing his meate, rubbing his Horſes, &amp;c. doeth by theſe Actions, as it were by ſolemne Signes acknowledge Civill homage to him, being a Civill Lord and Maiſter: So a Miniſter of the Goſpell and a Paſtor of a particular Congregation, beeing by his office a mere ſpirituall man; beeing commaunded by the Biſhop, as he is a ſpirituall Lord and Maiſter over the Church of God, To weare a Tippet, a ſquare cap, a Prieſtes Gowne &amp; Cloke, a Surplice: to make Croſſes upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> childes faces; To put Rings on Brides fingers, &amp;c. and all this in their Divine Service. I ſay a Miniſter doeth thereby give ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Signes and Tokens of ſpirituall homage to their ſpirituall Lordſhips, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as by preaching the Word &amp; Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Sacramentes &amp; prayer, he profeſſeth by ſolemne Signes a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall homage to the ſpirituall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:22"/>
            <p>If they ſhall peremptorilie affirme, That they are onely Civill matters (as ſome in high place have done to my ſelf) Then this will follow of it; Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Biſhops commaunde now Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters To weare a Surplice, a Prieſtes Cloke, &amp;c. hee may commaund them to weare Tawnie Cotes, &amp; livry clokes; &amp; in their courſes to waite and attend upon him, as ſerving Creatures: For there is no more civill authoritie ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in requiring the one, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, If the one as well as the other bee civill matters. Neither will it helpe their cauſe, That the Magiſtrate requireth theſe things to be done. For the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>aunding Eccleſiaſticall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be done, his commaundement doth no more make them civill, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his commanding the Sacraments &amp; other partes of Divine worſhip to bee admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, duly doeth make them, civill matters. For the ratificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by civill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie the Conſtitutions of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
<pb facs="tcp:13901:22"/> authoritie, doeth no more make them civill matters the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ratification and confirmation of civill matters, by Eccleſiaſticall authoritie doeth make them Eccleſiaſticall or ſpirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Though therefore there is none of us that ſtande out in theſe matters, but have ever been content to yeeld unto their Lordſhips all civill honor, ſuch as is given to Barons, Earles, Dukes, and Princes, yet except they were Gods &amp; Chriſtes, wee have no reaſon, to give ſpirituall homage unto them; which is it that in very deede they require in theſe things: And therefore hence it comes to paſſe, That as they turne out of their Pallaces, Thoſe ſervauntes that refuſe their liveries, and to doe their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Services, So as though they were Lords &amp; Maſters in the Church, They turne the Miniſters out of their offices, &amp; ſhut them out of the Church, if they refuſe to weare their ſpirituall Liveries, and to doe them ſpirituall and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:13901:23"/> Service. But I come to the ſecond part of the Aſſumption.</p>
            <q>II. That the authoritie of our Lorde Archbiſhops and Biſhops, is a uſurped au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</q>
            <p>This is ſufficiently proved of late by Mai. <hi>Iacob</hi> in his I. Aſſertion by many reaſons, Onely becauſe the weight of the Argument leaneth upon it, I will uſe one Reaſon.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>Thoſe Officers and Rulers in the Church that make claime to be of Divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, chalenge to them ſelves Apostolicall authoritie and Iuriſdiction as the onely Succeſſours of the Apostles; to ſitt onely in Moſes chaire; To have ſole power of the Keys; To cut from the viſible Church, &amp; receyue againe: To haue power of creating &amp; diſplacing all other Eccleſiasticall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers; To bee the Vniverſall Pastors of whole Dukedomes and Kingdomes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom all other Pastors are as Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, &amp;c. And yet for all this, are ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:13901:23"/> as ſtand &amp; are ſupported only by humane Traditions and Ceremonies, ſuch as a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Magistrate may without ſinne, put out of the Church, And ſuch as the true Churches of God may renounce (and yet continue the true Church) as Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vſurpers and ſpirituall Tyrants. (I ſay) all ſuch Officers &amp; Rulers exerciſe a uſurped authoritie in the Church:</item>
               <item>But our Archbiſhops &amp; Biſhops are ſuch Rulers and Officers as are aforeſaid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> They execute a Vſurped power over the Church.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition may eaſily be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. For it inferiour officers, <hi>viz.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of particular Congregations, have had and may have firme continuance in the Church, without theſe humane deviſes &amp; inventions; If the Magiſtrate cannot without ſinne put them out of the Church; And if thoſe can bee no true Churches that renounce to haue
<pb facs="tcp:13901:24"/> perticular Paſtors and Miniſters over them, It muſt much more hold in ſuch church-Officers &amp; Rulers as theſe are, if their authoritie be lawfull and good: For whileſt the Apoſtles lived, They needed not any humane Traditions &amp; diviſes to ſupport their authoritie: The Magiſtrates that ſought to putt them downe ſinned with a high hande: And that was no Church, that renounced and diſclaimed their Office, Authoritie and Iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is as eaſilie iuſtified. For 1. They make claime and Title to all thoſe Prerogatives before rehearſed in the firſt part of the Propoſition, and unto more then that, as ſhalbe proved if it be denied, 2. It is an Embleme of their own, <hi>NO CEREMONIE, NO BISHOP.</hi> Ergo, <hi>No humane Tradition and Invention, no Biſhop, Ergo,</hi> The office of a Biſhop is ſupported by them either only or ſpecially. 3. Their
<pb facs="tcp:13901:24"/> Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction is derived from the King, els it is a flat deniall of his Supremacie. Alſo them ſelves grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in their laſt Tables of Diſcipline, That the King hath power to increaſe or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Circuit of a Biſhopricke: That he may make two or more Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks of one, &amp; one Biſhoprick to be two or more: Yea what ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but that he may divide the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike of London into 800. For where God hath not defined the number of Pariſhes that a Biſhop is to raign over, it muſt needes bee a thing indifferent: in which by their owne Doctrines the King hath authoritie without ſinne, to diſpoſe. If therefore the King may as well (notwithſtanding any thing in the Law of God) Give the Keyes of the Church to everie particular Paſtour of a Congregation, over his owne Congregation, as to a Biſhop over a Dioceſſe, which taketh away the very Eſſence of an Engliſh Biſhop, He may
<pb facs="tcp:13901:25"/> without ſinne take away the very Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Biſhop, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtes in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Iuriſdiction over many Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Alſo it being not defined by the word of God, but left free what attire Biſhops ſhall weare, as alſo what main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance they ſhal have, The K. having abſolute power in things indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their owne Doctrine, hee may turne them out of their Rochetts and Parliament Robes. Thruſt them out of their Pallaces, and put them to their ſtipendes, to live upon voluntarie devotions of poore Chriſtian people, and then a man may eaſily imagine what the office of a Biſhop would bee worth: For he that hath authoritie to preſcribe to a Biſhop and other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Formes, Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their Divine Service, hath alſo power much more, To preſcribe, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and appointe their Apparell, Diet, and manner of maintenance. So that it is cleare, That the King may
<pb facs="tcp:13901:25"/> without ſinne diſanull the authorities, dignities and prerogatives of Biſhops. Any of which ſhalbe (if it bee denied) prooved to be matters of greater indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferencie, and therefore more appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his Supremacte, then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing of Formes of Divine Service and myſticall Rites of Religion. For let the King take from the Biſhop all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things (which he may doe by their owne doctrine) and a Biſhop will be no Biſhop, as ſhalbe prooved, if it be denied. 4. There is no true and ſober Chriſtians but will ſay that the Churches of <hi>Scotland, Fraunce,</hi> the low Countries, and other places (that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſuch Archbiſhops &amp; Biſhops (as ours are) as Antichriſtian and uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Prelates) are true Churches of God: which they could not bee, if the authorities &amp; prerogatives they claime to them ſelves, were of Chriſt, and not uſurped. For if it were the ordinance of Chriſt Ieſus, That in every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb facs="tcp:13901:26"/> that receaveth the Goſpel, There ſhould bee one Archbiſhop over the whole Kingdome: One Biſhop over many hundred Paſtors in a kingdome, and all they inveſted with that autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Apoſtolicall which they claime <hi>iure Divino,</hi> to be due vnto them, and to reſide in them, by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt, certainly that church that ſhould renounce and diſclaime ſuch an authoritie, ordayned in the Church, cannot be a true Church but a Synagogue of Sathan. For they that ſhould renounce and denie ſuch, muſt needes therein renounce and denie Chriſt him ſelfe. Thus the Aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is cleared.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:26"/>
            <head>The 11. Argument.</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All humane Traditions and Rites enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to bee performed in Gods Worſhip, as neceſſarie to Salvation, are unlawfull.</item>
               <item>Theſe Ceremonies in controverſie, beeing but Humane Traditions, are enioyned to bee performed in Gods worſhip, as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to Salvation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Theſe Ceremonies are unlawfull.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is freely graunted of all our Adverſaries hitherto. If anie heereafter bv reaſon of ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the cauſe may bee thruſt into by graunting the ſame, ſhalbe deſperate as to denie the ſame: we ſhalbe readie to make it good at any time.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:27"/>
            <p>The Aſſumption is thus prooved.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>What ſoever, Humane Tradition, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, or Action, That may without ſinne, or inconvenience to any part of the Worſhip of God, bee omitted in the ſame, and yet notwithstanding are inioyned and urged as more neceſſarie, then thoſe Actions that are by the woord of God neceſſarie to Salvation: I ſaye, ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ceremonies and Traditions, are inioyned as neceſſarie to Salvation.</item>
               <item>But theſe Ceremonies are ſuch, as may without any ſinne, or any inconvenience to any part of the Worſhip of God, bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the ſame, and yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are inioyned as more neceſſarie for Christians to doe, then thoſe Actions that are neceſſarie to Salvation by the Woord of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Theſe Ceremonies in controverſie are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned, &amp;c. as neceſſarie to ſalvation.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:27"/>
            <p>He hath no blood of ſhame running in his veines, that will deny the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption hath two partes:</p>
            <p>The firſt is this.</p>
            <q>That theſe Ceremonies are ſuch as may without ſinne or any inconvenience to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie part of the worſhip of God, bee omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</q>
            <p>This is evident: For 1. if they could not bee omitted without ſinne in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, they were Divine &amp; not Humane Ordinances. For example: Though to go clothed to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation be a Civill action, yet becauſe it is a ſinne, for any to goe naked to the Congregation, It is a Divine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, That men ſhould goe clothed thither. And in this caſe (as in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe of ſinne) a man ought rather never Worſhip God publicklie, then to goe naked to the Congregation. For the omiſſion of a Good action is
<pb facs="tcp:13901:28"/> no ſinne, when it can not be done, but by committing of a ſinne? 2. Divine Worſhip conſiſting in Prayer, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and the Word, no witt of man can ſhew wherein the bare omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any one of theſe Ceremonies is inconvenient to any one of theſe partes. For what inconvenience can a man (that is not drunk with the dreggs and lees of popiſh ſuperſtition) finde it to publike prayer, to bee ſaide in the Congregation without a Prieſtes Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice? The omiſſion of ordinarie Pawſes &amp; Accentes pointes &amp; ſtoppes, the ſuppreſſing of the voice, or a lowd whopping and hollowing out of the words, or an undiſtinct ſoundinge of them, were ſuch Actions as common reaſon will teach are inconvenient, for prayer, and ſo inconvenient that a man ought never to praye publikelie in the Congregation, as the voyce thereof, that ſhould by Canon be tied thereto: And the Magiſtrate (though there
<pb facs="tcp:13901:28"/> were no Canon to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie) ought to turne ſuch out of the Miniſtery that ſhould omitt ſuch matters in prayer. But for a Miniſter to pray without a Surplice, can be in reaſon no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, then for him to pray with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out booke, without a paire of Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles upon his noſe. And there may bee as good reaſon given to proove it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, for a man that ſaith a thinge without booke, to putt on a paire of Spectacles, as there can be to prove it convenient for him that is to praye in the Church, to putt upon him ſelfe a white linnen garment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Aſſumption is this:</p>
            <q>That they are inioyned as more neceſſary for Chriſtians to doe, then thoſe actions that by the worde of God are neceſſary to Salvation.</q>
            <p>Which I proove by this collection of Reaſons;</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:29"/>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>
                  <p>1. <hi>If the whole Solemne Worſhip and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Ieſus must ſtoupe and yeelde to theſe; And theſe must not ſtoupe or yeeld to them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>If thoſe that will yeeld to theſe are diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with for omiſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome duties that God requires of the Minister to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as neceſſarie to Salvation, and thoſe that are willing to doe all neceſſarie Services tending to the Salvation of Man, can not be diſpenced with for the Omiſsion of theſe, but must bee turned out of Christes Service.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. <hi>If thoſe that refuſe onely Conformitie to theſe are worſe then Idolatrous Papistes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4. <hi>If the bare omiſsion of theſe, though upon tenderneſſe of Coſscience, bee Sedition, Sciſme, Diſloyaltie, Rebellion, a deniall of the Kings Supremacie, Anabaptistrie, Frenzie, Worthie impriſonment, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, loſſe of Goods and living.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. <hi>If all that profeſſe theſe to bee unlawfull, are to be delivered up to Sathan, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathematized as men holding wicked &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13901:29"/> damnable errours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>6. <hi>If a man beeing in that Church, ought not to be of it where theſe Ceremonies are omitted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>7. <hi>If the bare omiſsion of theſe, make a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister by our law: more ſubiect to depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and ſuſpenſion, then the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the foulest Crimes, even Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, Blaſphemie, groſſe Ignorance, Vncleanneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>8. <hi>If her late Excellent Ma. Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſisted in theſe: I ſay, If all theſe Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bee true, then are they inioyned as more neceſſarie to bee done, then thoſe Actions that by the worde of God are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>But all theſe 8. pointes are to bee iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> Theſe Ceremonies are enioyned as more neceſſarie to bee done, then ſome Actions that are neceſſarie to Salvation.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:30"/>
            <p>The Propoſition can not be gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed. It being a Topick Axiom. <hi>Cuius privatio eſt deterior, illud ipſum eſt melius:</hi> to wit, The worſe the Privation of a thing is, the better the thing is. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: If blindnes be worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Then is the poſitive habit of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better then that of hearing. So, if Non-Conformitie be worſe then dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, blaſphemie, Idolatrie, Filthines of body, &amp;c. It muſt needs follow, that Conformitie is a more excellent thing in it ſelfe, then Sobrietie; the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; the glorifying of the name of God, then a chaſte and honeſt life: But all theſe are urged by the worde of God, as neceſſarie meanes to Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the holy Ghoſt ſaith: <hi>No Murderer, Adulterer, Vncleane perſon, Idolator, &amp;c. ſhall enter into the kingdome of heaven.</hi> If therefore Conformitie be more urged by our lawes, then theſe, and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation more puniſhed. If this be more ſtrictly required of Chriſtians, yea of
<pb facs="tcp:13901:30"/> principall Chriſtians, even the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the word, then the other, They muſt needes bee urged more neceſſarie to Salvation, then the other. For of the more excellencie a Chriſtian vertue is, the more neceſſarie to Salvation it is.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption in every part and parcell thereof may be iuſtified by the practiſe and Aſſertions of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, not onely privately but in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique. For the 1. God muſt not by Canon bee Worſhipped ſolemnely in England, except theſe be mingled with it, Though without them he might be never ſo well worſhipped. For the 2. Thoſe that yeeld to theſe, neede not preach at all in our church except they will, No nor to doe any other parte of Divine Service in their owne perſon, if they will maintayne a Curate, that will keepe the Ceremoniall Law, and faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Read or Sing the Kings Service, as they call it: And yet if preaching were not neceſſarie to Salvation, Paule that
<pb facs="tcp:13901:31"/> was above an Archbiſhop, ſhould not haue been under a woe, if hee had not done it. For no Miniſter of the Goſpell is under a woe That performeth all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to the Churches of God, that are neceſſarie to Salvation. Neither was Paules preaching, A reading of Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, or of a Service booke. For the 3. Nothing is more notorious then for us that make ſcruple of theſe things to be reputed worſe then Papiſtes: One that is a great Iudge in theſe cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, affirmed it unto my ſelfe. Another openly at Paules Croſſe in myne owne hearing, made no doubt but the Papiſtes were in the Church, but he made great doubt whether the Puritanes were. And yet we are Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes for nothing els but for refuſinge Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formitie to their Ceremonies: For howſoever they ſclaunder us with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other groſſe imputations, yet they can not laye any thing to our charge but our Conſcience in this. For all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13901:31"/> matters concerning their own eſtats, and dignityes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how deſperate they are, and unreformable we can be content to leaue them to the Iudgment of God, who (as it ſeemes) intendeth to gloryfie himſelf by ſome other meanes, then by then converſion. For the 4. Read <hi>Scottiſh. Genevat. The Survey, Remonſtraunce etc.</hi> And yea ſhal find all this laid to their charge. Alſo their practiſe ſufficiently proveth it, for the miniſters that are of late ſusſpended and deprived, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſing to uſe theſe Ceremonies, beare their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation vnder theſe names and Titles.</p>
            <p>The 5 and 6 is proved by their owne late Canons, ffor yf they bee to bee excommunicated <hi>ipſo ſacto</hi> as hould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing damnable &amp; wicked errours, that ſhall Profeſſe any of theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies to bee vnlawefull, a man ought not to acknowledge himſelf a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of any ſuch Churche, as doth
<pb facs="tcp:13901:32"/> affectedly caſt them out of gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: ffor for what error a perticular perſon is not to bee reputed a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Churche but as a heathen and publican, ffor the ſame a whole church is not to be reputed a church but a <hi>Sinagoge of Sathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 7 may be iuſtified by many inſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of many vile and impious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of thoſe kindes tolerated in the miniſtry.</p>
            <p>The <hi>8</hi> is proved by him that anſwers the <hi>Plea of the Innocent.</hi> Whoe <hi>Saith</hi> that they that call in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of theſe Ceremonies, call in queſtion hir late Maieſties Religion, which they could not doe, except (at the leaſt) parte of hir religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſiſted in them.</p>
            <p>Further yf this doth not ſufficiently proue the maine aſſumption, let theſe reaſons following be wayed.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> If the Church be neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and yf the pillars of the church
<pb facs="tcp:13901:32"/> be neceſſary to the Church, and if the lord Biſhops be the Pillars of the Church, and theſe or ſuch like Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies be the maine Supporters of L. Biſhops: then are theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the iudgment of the prelates, neceſſary to Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For no Church no Salvation, no pillor of the church no Church, no L. Biſhop no pillar of the Church, No ceremony no Lord Biſhop. <hi>Ergo no</hi> Ceremonie of this kinde, no Salvation.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> All divine conſtitutions binding conſcience are neceſſary to Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: But by the late doctrine of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and others, theſe Ceremonies (being not vnlawefull) when they ar commanded by the Church, are ſaid not to be humane but divine Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, binding conſcience; therfore they (as they are vrged) are neceſſary to Salvation. For all divine conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions binding conſcience, are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls nothing on
<pb facs="tcp:13901:33"/> our part can be ſaid in any ſence to be neceſſary thereunto.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> It is neceſſary to Salvation, that men ſhould not only worſhip God, but worſhip him in a comly decent and orderly manner, it being a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of damnation to worſhip God in a confuſed vnſeemely and diſordered manner, but by the doctrine of our Prelates, comelines, decencie, and order conſiſts, in the vſe of theſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, <hi>Ergo</hi> in their Iudgment, they are neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <p>Ob. The Church doth not intende to vrge theſe thinges as neceſſary to Saluation. <hi>Ergo,</hi> They are not urged, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <p>Anſ. 1 The Churche vrgeth not theſe things at all, but onely <hi>3</hi> or <hi>4</hi> Biſhops in the Churche, whiche (if theyr owne doctrine be true (are Vſurpers over our Churches, &amp; not ſo much as any true members of a Church.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> what if the Synode ſhould decree
<pb facs="tcp:13901:33"/> that the Kinge ſhould hould the arch biſhop ſtirrop, and the Prnce &amp; Nob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les kiſſe his Toe, once or twice a year and withall they ſhould proteſt, that they doe not require this as a worſhip or honor to the Archbiſhop but only for Comelines Order &amp; Edification were not this a ſhamefull ſhift as bad, as the thing it ſelf.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="argument">
            <head>The 12 Argument</head>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All actions, not required by the word of God (though commanded by humane authoritie) that are apparent meanes of the Damnation of the Soules of infinite numbers of men, are directly againſt the Lawe of charitie, and therefore Sin.</item>
               <item>But theſe Ceremonies are ſuch Actions</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is without queſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. For if without commandiment from God, I may vpon the ſole will and pleaſure of the Magiſtrate, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors
<pb facs="tcp:13901:34"/> of the Church, doe that by which I ſhalbe a means of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of my brothers Soule, which is the greateſt breach of the lawe of charitie that can bee. Then may I do any ſinn at theyr Commaundement without ſinn, for what greater ſinne can there be againſt the <hi>2</hi> Table then this, to be a witting inſtrument of my Neighbours Damnation. Which though it be but a matter of Ieſt to our greate Doctors that haue many Cures, and no care of Soules, yet to them which know the price of a ſoul it is more then if vpon the more will of the Magiſtrates they ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced to kill their owne Children and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loveds, with their owne hand.</p>
            <q>OB. The Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>are hauing authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e given him by God to commaund things Indifferent, he commaunding th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are to be done notwithſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>candall of our Nighbour.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:34"/>
            <p>Anſw. 1 Though the Subiect ought to obey his Magiſtrate in all Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent actions impoſed vpon him what ſoever, yet I deſier that it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that God in his word hath given to any Power or Potentate vpon Earth, any ſuch abſolute authoritie. The Magiſtrate is Gods Leifetenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and the glorie of the Magiſtrate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in this, in that vnder God hee beareth a ſword, to puniſh thoſe that tranſgreſſe his Lawes, but hee is by Gods Ordinaunce to be the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and protector of the chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, of his ſubiects, That therfore he hath power graunted him of God (vpon his owne pleaſure) to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſame, eſpecially inſuch a caſe requires profe out of the word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If he have ſuch a power, yet thoſe things that God leaues to his will to commaund, or not to commaund, he cannot commaund vnder a greater
<pb facs="tcp:13901:35"/> penaltie then bodily death; for his ſword can cutt no deeper, and then in the caſe of Scandall a chriſtian ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect ought rather to ſuffer the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to take away his life, then to doe that which ſhall procure the Damnation of his Brothers Soule. And in thus doing, he is noe contem nor of the Magiſtrates Lawe, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fulfiller of the Lawe of Charitie, in not diſtroying his brothers Soule vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſure of a mortall man.</p>
            <q>OB. But the commaundiment of the Magiſtrate takes away the ſcandall. When the thing is done in obedience to him.</q>
            <p>An. This is a nother deſperate ſhift As though the conſcience of the weake brother that iudgeth a thing indifferent to be a Sinne wilbe ever the more ſatiſfied and releeved in the matter by the authoritie of the Magiſtrate, nothing but the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God either can or ought to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie
<pb facs="tcp:13901:35"/> a doubting conſcience. And as for them that put ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in things Indiffrent, and are that way ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized the authoritie of the Magiſtrate or church commaunding them, their ſcandall is increaſed, and not remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the ſame.</p>
            <q>OB: But wee muſt more reſpect Obedience to the Magiſtrate, then the ſcandall of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour perſons, the thing commaunded being indifferent, and not evell.</q>
            <p>Anſ. 1 The thing commanded is not Indiffrent, then when it is a ſcandall, and ſtumbling block to our brother. 2: Wee muſt obay the Magiſtrate on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the Lord, but this is not to obay him in the Lord, onely vpon his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur to deſtroy a ſoule for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt died. 3. An obedience to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ſo far as to the condemnation of our brothers ſoule, muſt be a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall obedience, in ſome ſpeciall good and iuſt commandiment which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be verified of a commaundiment
<pb facs="tcp:13901:36"/> that requireth onely a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, much les ſuch an indifferent, as is a ſcandall and meanes of diſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to mens ſoules</p>
            <p n="4">4 Such a forbeareing of obedience onely in loue to the ſalvation of our brothers Soule, being without appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent contempt of the Magiſtrate, and having adioined with it, a meeke ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the mercie of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, cannot be called a diſſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. but is in deed a better obedienc then theirs, that doe contrarie, whoe in their obedience bring the bloud of the ſoules they deſtroy, both vpon their owne heads and the Magiſtrate which is a ſinn in the eyes of God wors then rebellion.</p>
            <q>OB. But by obedience to theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies many ſoules by meanes of preaching are ſaved, which ſhall want the meanes in the refuſall.</q>
            <p>Anſ. 1 Wee muſt not diſtroy the ſoules of ſome, that we may ſaue the
<pb facs="tcp:13901:36"/> ſoules of other, wee muſt doe that which is iuſt, though the world goe to wreck for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The greateſt good that a man can doe, cannot counteervaile the leaſt evill, much les ſo great an evell as to bee a witting inſtrument of the damnation of a brothers ſoule.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Hee that preacheth cannot aſſure himſelf of the ſalvation of one ſoule by the ſame, for that is wrought by the worke of the ſpirite of God And he hath litle cauſe to hope for a bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon that preaching, which hee purchaſeth with the price of blood, yea of the blood of ſoules.</p>
            <q>OB: But the K. the Magiſtrats &amp; ſtate are ſcandalized alſo at the omiſſion of them, and their ſcandall is more to be reſpected then the ſcandall of inferiour parſons, for the vſeing of them.</q>
            <p>Anſ. 1. For his Maieſtie, we doubt not but (if the prelates would) hee would eaſily yeald to the removall of
<pb facs="tcp:13901:37"/> them, and therfore he cannot be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dalized at the refuſall, when it is of meere conſcience, though of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence deceived. 2 The States and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Magiſtrates of the kingdome, have in all Parliaments ſhewed them ſelues willing, and ready, to ſet their handes to the removall of them. 3 If the King &amp; State wilbe ſcandalized, becauſe upon their mere will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I will not doe that which I am perſwaded will be a meanes of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction of their ſoules for whom Chriſt died. They wilbe much more ſcandalized at me if I doe it, For ſuch an obeydience as this, muſt needs be a meanes of begetting or confirming ſtraing ſinns in their ſoules, for as it is a kind of deifiyng of themſelues, To require (even in the caſe of ſcandall) a thing indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be done; ſo they that ſhall in ſuch a caſe obey, cannot but nuriſh exceedingly that corrupti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on from wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maudement
<pb facs="tcp:13901:37"/> ſhall proceed. 4 The ſoule of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and pooreſt in a kingdom coſt as great a price, and is as dear to Chriſt, as the ſoule of the Nobleſt, and in the matter of ſcandall as great heed is to be taken to them, as to any other: And it ſhewes of what ſpirit theſe men are of, that thinke they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the ſoules of Chriſts little ones. rather then diſpleaſe a mortall man.</p>
            <q>Ob. What? Muſt the Magiſtrates lawes be chaunged, for every humour that will pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend ſcandall?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſw.</hi> Yea, ſuch lawes as commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d onely <hi>thinges indifferent,</hi> in caſes of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſcandall are to be chaunged, of particular ſcandall, are (at the leaſt) to be diſpenced withall; For if laws that commaund things neceſſary are ſom times to be diſpenced with, and if of them it is ſaid. <hi>Extreeme right, is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme wrong.</hi> Much more then ſuch lawes as require onely ſuch things as are indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 1 Such things that (but
<pb facs="tcp:13901:38"/> for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunders pleaſure) makes noe matter whether they be done or noe. Which are indeed vnworthy to be commaunded of worthies. 2 A pretended ſcandall in humor is eaſily diſcerned by thoſe that are wiſe and not malicious, for they that are ready to performe all obedience to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate in all other heavier &amp; greater thinges, are ready in his ſervice to ſpend their goods &amp; lyues, that think nothing to deare for the redee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yng of his ſafety, that are in all other things as obedient, and more obedient then any other of his ſubiects: It is not to be ſuppoſed of any, (that are not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with the malicious ſpirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.) That ſuch ſhould refuſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Kings pleaſure in a toye, and a trifle, (ſuch as are all things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) except that in obeying him, they were perſwaded that they ſhould ſin againſt their own conſcience, which next vnto God, they haue cauſe to
<pb facs="tcp:13901:38"/> pleaſe, farr aboue all the Kings of the earth, for it hath greater power to tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment them, then they haue.</p>
            <p>But I proue the Aſſumption.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All apparent meanes of confirmyng me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Sciſme, Superſtition, and Idolatry, by meanes wherof many haue profeſedly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and dyed therein, without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce: are apparent meanes of the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and deſtruction of many ſoules amongſt us:</item>
               <item>But Theſe Ceremonyes are ſuch.</item>
               <item>Ergo.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The propoſition canot be denyed, for what action of man can be ſayde to be a meanes of the damnation and deſtruction of anothers ſoule: If thes actions be not that confirme men in ſuche foule Sinnes: So that either a man can doe nothinge that ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his brothers ſoule (which is dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt the expreſſe wordes of St. Paule,) Or els ſuch a conformitie, in ſuch actions as Confirme men in ſuch Damnable Sinnes, doth deſtroy
<pb facs="tcp:13901:39"/> his ſoule.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is as evident as any ſuch matter can be. For</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The Papiſts not onely amongſt vs (which are innumerable) but others alſo doe profeſſe, that by our vſe of thes Ceremonies) which are conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated myſteryes of their owne Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) they are confirmed in the truth of their Religion, and the falſhood of ours. And good reaſon they haue ſo to iudge: For if the broth be good that the Divill is ſod in, ſure the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill himſelf muſt needs be good alſo. 2 Thoſe chriſtians of the Seperation that are called <hi>Browniſts</hi> being many hundreds, profesſing the ſame faith that we doe, are by the retayning of Reliques, confirmed in their Sciſme, and Seperation from vs; And liue &amp; dye in this opinion: <hi>That our Churches are noe true Churches,</hi> and <hi>that a man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without ſinn communicate with them.</hi> And the maine ground of this is, for
<pb facs="tcp:13901:39"/> that we mingle with Divine worſhip theſe baſe &amp; vile inventions of men, Yea, of the accurſſed Anti-chriſt. What? Is a linnen ragg, and a chriſts croſſe &amp;c. to be reputed of ſo great va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lue &amp; price, that the fellowſhip &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall communion of ſo many chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, (as ſound in religion as any pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late in the Realme) ſhould be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reiected for them?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Common experience teacheth us, that there are infinit numbers in this realme, ignorant &amp; ſuperſtitious folk, that place as much, or more holynes in theſe thinges, then in the holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces of God; And how can it be otherwiſe, when they ſhall ſee the Rulers of the Church, mingle Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Earth, and Hell together in this manner about them. Curſing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathematizing all that ſhall not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them. How can they but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, that the ſight of a ſurplice upon a preiſts back ſhall bring them to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb facs="tcp:13901:40"/> when they ſhall ſee thoſe that keep Heaven Keyes, ſend a man, for want of ſuch a wedding garment, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> to Hell?</p>
            <p n="4">4 If it be but conſidered, that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proteſtant Churches haue reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them as menſtrous clothes, that more then the greateſt number of Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtors in our owne Land, that deſires the name of faithfull &amp; painfull Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, either count them impious, or at leaſt the burdens, or reproches of our Churches: that the firſt appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of them, (after our ſeperation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome) intended only a toleration of them, that the moſt ſcandalous and lewd perſons in our congregations, are the hotteſt for them, that every Parliament ſince hir Maieſties raigne hath been forward in the removing of them, that the defence of them hath driven men to runne into the broching of many groſſe and popiſh e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> And that ſo many miniſters,
<pb facs="tcp:13901:40"/> (a catalogue of whoſe names and ſtates, I could wiſh were publiſhed to all poſterity, that it may ſee the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull milde &amp; moderate goverme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of prelates) haue indured and expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted daylie to indure the greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremityes for the ſame: I ſay, if theſe thinges be duely conſidered, a man ſhall eaſily ſee, that theſe ceremonyes are ſtumbling blocks, layd by the De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vill and his Agents in the wayes of all the people of this Realme, to hinder the progreſſe of the Goſpell, and to make all men ſtumble in the wayes of Salvation.</p>
            <trailer>How long Lord Ieſus.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:41"/>
            <head>AN ADDITION.</head>
            <p>NOt onely our Conformers unto Rome, but they alſo that abhorre the ſame, can hardly indure to heare, <hi>that theſe ceremonyes are parts of divine worſhip,</hi> for whoſe further ſatisfaction I ad this one Argument.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>Whatſoever being vſed in dyuine worſhipe is directly contrary to the <hi>.2.</hi> Commaundement, is a part of dyuine w rſhipe.</item>
               <item>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ceremonies are vſed in Dyuine Worſhip &amp; are directly contrary to the <hi>2.</hi> commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               <item>Ergo</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Propoſition is evident, for all outwarde Idolatry is Dyuine worſhipp &amp; nothing but Outwarde Idolatry is <hi>directly</hi> forbidden in the .2. Commaundement.</p>
            <p>The .2. part of the Aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is thus proued,</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>All inventions and deviſes of man, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only vpon the will of man, and not upon any neceſſitie of nature, or civility, ſet a part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God outward wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhip are contrary to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmaund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</item>
               <item>Theſe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nye are ſuch,</item>
               <item>Ergo.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The propoſition we proue thus.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>Either all ſuch deviſes and inventions are contrary vnto t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſecond commaundement, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their is no<note n="*" place="margin">A trope or figure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>each wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in vnder o e k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nde of Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ts d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den.</note> Synechdoche theirin,</item>
               <item>But ther is a Synechdoche in the <hi>2</hi> commaund<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement.</item>
               <item>Ergo.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:41"/>
            <p>The Aſſumption or latter part of this Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyſme cannot be denyed of any, but ſuch as ſhall deſperatly ſett themſelues, againſt the truth of God. For if their were no figure or Trope in the commaundement, then to bowe downe vnto, &amp; to worſhip the Sunn, Moone and Starrs, or any other of Gods creatures, yea, or any image made by any other, ſhould be no breach of this commaundement, much les to offer Iewiſh Sacrifices of ſheep &amp; Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, to circumciſe, to goe a pilgrimage to Sai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to kiſſe the Paxe, to ſprinckle with holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to Baptiſe Bells, or to uſe any other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh rites, in which if a man ſinne not againſt the ſecond commaundement, he ſinneth not againſt any. Againe, it would be demaunded, againſt what commaundement, <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> ſinned, when they offred ſtrang fire. The Iſraelits when they abuſed Gideons E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod, Iudg. 8 27. The Corinthians in eating meate offred to Idols in the Idols temples, 1 Cor. 9. Either they ſinned not again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this commaundement, and by conſequent againſt none, or els there muſt needs be, a wonderfull large Trope in the ſame, which I think never any divine Iew or Chriſtian, Proteſtant or Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſt ever denyed before now.</p>
            <p>The propoſition is as evident if it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that in the 2 commaundement, literally
<pb facs="tcp:13901:42"/> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeach, nothing is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or worſhip, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto them, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, now i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there be a Synechdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ndement, ther muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not onely other kindes of falſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>p of Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>latry, different in forme from making, &amp; bowing downe unto Images &amp; Ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, but their mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſo ſome common ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or ground, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on which makeing &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> unto Images is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>dden, which muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Argument, and reaſon by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> outward worſhip are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> images, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at, els <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t were ſenceleſſe to make a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y thinge t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at attempt a bowinge downe vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ges t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der that name &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is condemned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e that thing doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>ate with i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame cauſe for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it is c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>mned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tor example i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto Images<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them. Now
<pb facs="tcp:13901:42"/> let all the witts in the world lay theyr heades together &amp; they ſhall neuer be able to deviſe any ſuch common <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that ſhalbe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cauſe why not only <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> downe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> but why un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er it an other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nde or Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and falſe worſhips is condemned, but this. for that they were <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mane devices, &amp; inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and therefore under the moſt u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uall and generall receaved invention of man, God con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demneth all other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to the ſame end. If this be not the reaſon then ther are &amp; may be infinite, Out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Idolatries &amp; Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions that cannot with any reaſon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to this commaundement. Therfore it muſt needs follow that either ther is no tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e in the commaundemente or that all ſuch <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntions</hi> of man are forbid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en in the ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>An advertiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment.</head>
            <p>I had thought (good re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er) to haue fortified ſome other poynts in the Arguments, which to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doe not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider may ſeem weake, but I forbeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſome ſpeciall reaſons, I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly to admon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h thee of one de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> me. viz. The mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng of the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ps Argument thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it better t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> was, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or thus it is, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> been pour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13901:43"/> good, are lawfull and good ceremonyes.</item>
               <item>The doctrine of theſe ceremonyes is ſound and good,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Which is ſubiect to the very ſame abſurdityes that the other and more alſo. For 1 the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of them is unſound &amp; falſe, for the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of them is this, that they are matters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, of order decency, and edification, no parts of Divine worſhip, that they are Sciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matickes that will not conforme unto them, enimyes to the Supremacy and State, that it is a wicked error to hould them unlawfull &amp; ſuperſtitious that they are to be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated that affirme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſo. etc. All which is unſound doctrine concernyng them. 2 Graunt the doctrine ſound, yet it followeth not that the Ceremonyes are good, for the thing may be wicked, and yet the doctryne of it ſound. For, There is a ſound doctrine of all Vices. 3 In what reſpect doth he affirme the doctrine to be ſound and good? Is it not from the uſe and end that is aſſigned unto them by himſelf? Becauſe they are appoynted for ſuch &amp; ſuch ends? Hence will follow the very ſame abſurdities, that I haue obſerved in the former. For then any ridiculous or baſe Ceremony, may be inſtituted, ſo it be under pretence of a good end.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13901:43"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
